Guide to the Peter Goin, Nuclear Landscapes
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Peter Goin, Nuclear Landscapes: Portfolio of Forty-Four Photographs and Trinity Panorama.
2011-2011
WA Photos Folio 163
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
in 2 boxes (44 inkjet prints, 41 x 51 cm, and 1 inkjet print, 46 x 155 cm)
Portfolio of inkjet prints of photographs by Peter Goin that document nuclear test sites in Nevada and the Marshall Islands, as well as a and a radioactive waste repository in Washington, circa 1986-1988, and printed in 2011.
Goin, Peter, 1951-
Blesse, Robert E.
Hinton, Scott C., 1974-
Black Rock Press
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Peter Goin on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2015.
Peter Goin (born 1951)
Peter Goin is an American photographer known for his work within the altered landscape.
Scott C. Hinton (born 1974)
Scott C. Hinton is an American photographer and printer.
Robert E. Blesse (born 1946)
Robert E. Blesse is an American special collections librarian and director of the Black Rock Press of the University of Nevada, Reno, Library.
Scope and Contents
Portfolio of inkjet prints of photographs by Peter Goin that document nuclear test sites at Nevada Test Site, Nevada, and at Bikini Atoll and Enewetak Atoll in the Marshall Islands, as well as the radioactive waste repository at Hanford Site, Washington, circa 1986-1988. Printed by Scott C. Hinton in 2011. The portfolio includes a title page printed by Robert E. Blesse of the Black Rock Press. Most of the images appeared in Peter Goin, Nuclear Landscapes (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1991).
Limited edition of 3; Beinecke copy is no. 3.
Nuclear weapons -- Marshall Islands -- Testing -- Pictorial works; Nuclear weapons -- Nevada -- Testing -- Pictorial works; Radioactive waste repositories -- Washington (State) -- Pictorial works; Bikini Atoll (Marshall Islands) -- Pictorial works; Enewetak Atoll (Marshall Islands) -- Pictorial works; Hanford Site (Wash.) -- Pictorial works; Marshall Islands -- Pictorial works; Nevada -- Pictorial works; Nevada Test Site (Nev.) -- Pictorial works; New Mexico -- Pictorial works; Trinity Site (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Washington (State) -- Pictorial works; White Sands Missile Range (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Panoramas; Photographs; Goin, Peter, 1951-; Blesse, Robert E.; Goin, Peter, 1951-; Hinton, Scott C., 1974-; Black Rock Press
- Inkjet Prints, 2011; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Inkjet prints of photographs by Peter Goin that document nuclear test sites at Nevada Test Site, Nevada, and at Bikini Atoll and Enewetak Atoll in the Marshall Islands, as well as the radioactive waste repository at Hanford Site, Washington, circa 1986-1988, and printed by Scott C. Hinton in 2011.
  The inkjet prints are on Canson Infinity Rag Photographique paper, 310 grams per square meter. The prints have images 28 x 36 cm on paper 41 x 51 cm except for the panorama, which has an image 36 x 146 cm on paper 46 x 155 cm. Captions also appear in the printed images. Versos signed and numbered by the photographer.
  The title page is printed on Rives BFK heavyweight tan paper, 280 grams per square meter, by Robert E. Blesse of the Black Rock Press, and uses a graphic created by Goin.
  The title for each print is followed by parenthetical expressions that first document Goin's negative number and secondly provide the page number that the image appeared in Goin's, Nuclear Landscapes (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1991) or if it did not appear in the book. Notes provide description of the images by Goin.
  The prints are housed into two custom portfolio cases with sheets of acid-free paper interleaved by the creators.
  Laid in box 1 is a checklist and colophon information as well as a biographical statement for Goin.
  Arrangement
  Following the title page, the inkjet prints are organized and arranged into three categories by Goin: Nevada Test Site, Nevada; Hanford Nuclear Reservation, Washington; and Marshall Islands, followed by a panorama of the Trinity Site at the White Sands Missile Range, New Mexico.
  - Title page, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Nevada Test Site, Nevada
    - 1. Subsidence Craters (CA86) (not in book), 2011 (Box 1)
      "North end of Yucca Flat looking east at Papoose Range and subsidence craters."
    - 2. Subsidence Crater (CB49) (page 59), 2011 (Box 1)
      "Since 1963, in accordance with the Limited Test Ban Treaty, all nuclear tests have been conducted underground. This crater resulted from the collapse of earth into the cavity created by an underground nuclear detonation. The test shafts are usually drilled about 1,500 feet deep."
    - 3. Sedan Crater (CB48) (page 63), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This crater remains from the Plowshares program, the purpose of which was to test the peaceful use of nuclear explosions. The operating hypothesis was that a nuclear explosion could easily excavate a large area, facilitating the building of canals and roads, improving mining techniques, or simply moving a large amount of rock and soil. The intensity and distribution of radiation proved too great, and the program was abandoned. The 'Sedan' device was thermonuclear - 70 percent fusion, 30 percent fission - with a yield of 100 kilotons. The crater is an impressive 635 feet deep and 1,280 feet wide. The weight of the material lifted was 12 million tons."
    - 4. Destroyed Road Crater (CB52) (page 51), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This road was constructed along the northeastern edge of Yucca Flat and used in preparation for an underground nuclear test. A drilling crew then prepared the site for ground zero - right in the middle of the road, about 1,500 feet below the surface. The detonation destroyed the road and created this subsidence crater (the ground collapses into the cavity by the blast)."
    - 5. Overgrown Road Crater (CB56) (not in book), 2011 (Box 1)
      "After a subterranean nuclear test, an area larger than the diameter of the cavity was declared off-limits and marked by fences with yellow ropes. Because this road was within the test zone, it was closed off. No longer in use, the road collects scarce rainwater, creating an environment conducive to overgrowth. This subsidence crater is located along the northeastern edge of Yucca Flat."
    - 6. Accelerated Erosion (CB62) (page 55), 2011 (Box 1)
      "The U.S. Geological Survey made a perpendicular cut into a fault zone that runs north to south in the valley floor at Yucca Flat. The orange lines were painted in the dirt to measure the shift of alluvial deposits resulting from nuclear testing. The breaks in the line reflect the degree of the fault shift."
      Title in book is "Fault Zone."
    - 7. Site of Above-Ground Tests, Yucca Lake (CB76) (page39), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This is the dry playa of Frenchman Lake in Yucca Flat seen from the top of 'News Knob,' the location of the press gallery during the above-ground testing days. Many of the scientific photographs of mushroom clouds were also taken from this point. Joshua trees once again pepper the desert floor (foreground)."
    - 8. Ground Zero Tower (CB66) (page 37), 2011 (Box 1)
      "In the above-ground test conducted on this site, the nuclear device was positioned on top of a tall tower for detonation. The great force of the blast caused the tower to disintegrate, leaving only its base. The land in this area is still contaminated with alpha particles, although the surface has been bulldozed."
    - 9. Cement Test Structures (CB82) (page 41), 2011 (Box 1)
      "A variety of structures was tested for resistance to nuclear explosions. Buildings such as these at Frenchman Lake, Yucca Flat, are located throughout the above-ground testing area at different angles and distance from ground zero. The tank, far left, remains highly radioactive."
    - 10. Collapsed Hangar (CB84) (page 45), 2011 (Box 1)
      "Only the skeleton of this hangar remained after it endured the nuclear winds from a blast at Frenchman Lake, Yucca Flat."
    - 11. Enclosed Electrified Fence (CB88) (page 47), 2011 (Box 1)
      "Positioned at different distances from ground zero, enclosures like this one and the one visible beyond it (on the left) contained animal subjects during a variety of tests at Frenchman Lake, Yucca Flat."
    - 12. Railroad Trestle (CA93) (page 43), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This surviving trial railroad trestle stands in Frenchman's Lake, Yucca Flat. This bridge, the only remaining section of an elevated railroad, was located 1,800 feet from ground zero and received overpressures exceeding 450 pounds per square inch. The blast blew sections of the structure off the foundation and bent large I-beam girders. This detonation, code named 'Pricilla,' had 37 kilotons of force. By comparison, the blast at Hiroshima measured 13 kilotons."
    - 13. How Would a House Withstand Nuclear Wind? (CB69) (page 49), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This building was part of a 'doom town,' consisting of houses, office buildings, fallout shelters, power systems, communications equipment, a radio broadcasting station, and trailer homes. This house was 7,500 feet from ground zero. In a test called 'Apple II,' fired on 5 May 1955, the entire foundation shifted from the force of the 29-kiloton blast. The house has been partially restored to document the historical importance of the above-ground testing period."
    - 14. Dry Sump Pond, Yucca Flat (CA94) (page 35), 2011 (Box 1)
      "Drilling for a detonation site requires the storage of displaced earth and water. This dry sump pond is no longer in use. The drill site has been preserved for an upcoming test, yet to be determined. The two towers remain from the drilling process."
    - 15. Fire Burn (CA82) (not in book), 2011 (Box 1)
      "Big Burn Valley looking down [Fortymile] Canyon. Funeral Range farthest visible range."
    - 16. Accelerated Erosion (CA79) (page 53), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This canyon is in the South Silent Canyon area on the grounds of the Nevada Test Site. Although the area is not used for testing it demonstrates the accelerated erosion caused by nuclear testing nearby. Vibrations from underground testing fracture the rock cliffs, breaking loose huge boulders."
    - 17. Yucca Flat (CA99) (page 61), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This view at the west end of Yucca Flat shows the shadow of the Eleana Mountain Range along its alluvial plane. Numerous above-ground tests were conducted in this area."
    - 18. Subterranean Test, Ground Zero (CB91) (page 57), 2011 (Box 1)
      "A recent underground test was conducted here on Pahute Mesa. Ground Zero was where equipment appears, in the lower left comer of the photograph. Although the surrounding area is composed of rock rather than sediment, and a subsidence crater therefore did not form at the time of the test, geologists cannot guarantee that one will not develop in the future. The large flat area that resembles a baseball diamond was cleared to accommodate numerous trailers containing evaluation equipment. The blast caused accelerated rock erosion in the bluffs visible at middle distance."
    - 19. Yucca Mountain (CA91) (page 33), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This view of Jackass Flats, bordered by Skull (center) and Little Skull (far right) mountains was taken from the top of Yucca Mountain. Yucca Mountain is a proposed disposal site for high-level nuclear wastes from across the country."
  - Hanford Nuclear Reservation, Washington
    Also known as Hanford Site.
    - 20. Orchard Site (NLS18) (page 67), 2011 (Box 1)
      "Hanford and White Bluffs, Washington, were successful farming regions. This orchard was cut down after the area was condemned for use in the Hanford Nuclear Reservation."
    - 21. Burial Ground (NLS74) (page 99), 2011 (Box 1)
      "In this burial ground contaminated material ranging from radioactive soil to radioactive tools, clothing, and equipment is buried under river rock. This site is near the nuclear reactor across from the White Bluffs area of the Columbia River."
    - 22. Waste Storage Pond (NLS60) (page 75), 2011 (Box 1)
      "Bright sunlight reflects off the standing water in a liquid waste disposal pond for Nuclear Reactors D and DR. The water is contaminated with radioactivity. The reactor grounds are surrounded by security fences and laced with power lines."
    - 23. Contaminated Overflow Drain (NLS58) (page 93), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This drain housing on the Columbia River was surrounded and covered with fencing, to keep out all wildlife, including birds. The reactor drain is no longer in use, but the structure remains severely contaminated."
    - 24. Tracks (NLS51) (page 89), 2011 (Box 1)
      "These abandoned and overgrown railroad tracks served a nuclear reactor located along the Columbia River near the old White Bluffs town site."
    - 25. Nuclear Reactors (NLS65) (page 77), 2011 (Box 1)
      "These reactors are now decommissioned. D Reactor was one of the three original reactors built between 1943 and 1945. The 'R' in DR stands for "replacement." The yellow posts identify buried radioactive waste and potential surface contamination."
      Title in book is "Nuclear Reactors D and DR."
    - 26. Burial Gardens (NLS27) (page 97), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This trench is located in the geographic center of the Hanford Nuclear Reservation and is called the Burial Gardens. Contaminated materials are loaded into a variety of containers-barrels, crates, sheds-and stored in open trenches. When a trench is full it is backfilled and marked with yellow posts identifying the presence of radioactivity. The buildings in the background (left and right) are plutonium metallurgical laboratories and incinerators."
      The image is different from the book image; both are from the same area at Hanford.
    - 27. Submarine Reactor Disposal Site (NLS17) (page 81), 2011 (Box 1)
      "The nuclear reactor compartment from the decommissioned submarine Patrick Henry was part of a very long funeral journey. Starting in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, the nuclear remains traveled down the Ohio and Mississippi rivers, into the Gulf of Mexico, through the Panama Canal, up the Pacific Coast, and finally inland on the Columbia River to Hanford, where it arrived in April 1986. Land disposal was selected for reactor compartments and sea burial for the remainder of the submarine. The excavation for the reactor is 200 feet by 200 feet by 50 feet. Each compartment is 38 feet long, 30 feet in diameter, and weighs over 1,000 tons. The compartment hull will resist corrosion for at least 200 years, and the reactor pressure vessel for 1,000 years. More compartments· will be deposited here before burial is finally completed."
    - 28. Potential Nuclear Waste Area (NLS35) (page 79), 2011 (Box 1)
      "During the 1980s, the Department of Energy studied locations in Nevada, Texas, and Washington to find sites for the long-term underground storage of high-level nuclear waste. Because Hanford was already a nuclear area, this site was chosen as one of three possible national storage areas. The dominant subsurface basalt formations were thought to be suitable "containers" for nuclear waste. This is the entrance to one of three test tunnels in the Near-Surface Test Facility. The tunnels have been sealed, and plans for storing waste in this area have been suspended in response to objections voice by Washington political delegations."
  - Marshall Islands
    - 29. Ground Zero (NLS118) (page 103), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This water-filled crater, located at the northern tip of Runit Island, Enewetak Atoll, was made by the 'Lacrosse' detonation (40 kilotons) during Operation Redwing in 1956. The water is no longer radioactive."
    - 30. Nuclear Bunker (NLS191) (page 109), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This University of California Radiation Laboratory photo station bunker was constructed for Operation Castle (19 54) on Aerkijlal Island, Bikini Atoll. Note the six cement support housings for heavy-duty iron beams used to brace the bunker against the force of the nuclear blast. The bunker withstood the blast, and the beams were later removed."
    - 31. Nuclear Bunker Complex (NLS158) (page 158), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This is Station 1310, an alpha recording diagnostic measurement station used on Operation Redwing (1956) and Operation Hardtack (1958) on Runit Island, Enewetak Atoll. This area is radioactive."
    - 32. Tide Pool (NLS144) (page 145), 2011 (Box 1)
      "Because the amount of electrical and mechanical equipment used in the nuclear testing operations was so massive, even the best cleanup efforts could not remove all the electrical wire, pipe, and assorted smaller mechanical objects. Some were welded naturally into the coral tidal areas throughout Bikini and Enewetak atolls, creating an unnatural beauty. The Marshall Island sites of Bikini and Enewetak are still radioactive."
    - 33. Nuclear Bunker Complex (NLS221) (page 115), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This bunker complex was a photographic station and optical station used during Operation Redwing (1956) and subsequent operations on Aomen Island, Bikini Atoll. Several lead bricks can be seen in center foreground at the water's edge. These were used in constructing radiation barriers."
    - 34. Abandoned Bunker (NLS140) (page 111), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This was Station 77. The left door was the entrance to the timing and firing distribution station; the right door led to the telephone switchboard; and the structure on the roof (Station 1511) housed camera mounts. These were constructed for Operation Redwing (19 56) on Runit Island, Enewetak Atoll. Shifting sands have caused this bunker to lean toward the water."
      Title in book is "Nuclear Bunker."
    - 35. Ruin (NLS160) (page 139), 2011 (Box 1)
      "As part of the entertainment facilities for test site personnel, a Greek theater was constructed on Enewetak Island."
      Title in book is "Abandoned Amphitheater."
    - 36. Bunker Complex (NLS208) (page 131), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This bunker on Nam Island, Bikini Atoll, was built for the test known as 'Cherokee' in Operation Redwing (1956). 'Cherokee' was detonated directly overhead; so the bunker, which was unmanned but contained sensitive and delicate instrumentation, needed to be massive. This reinforced concrete cube measured 24 feet on its exterior side: the walls - top, bottom, and ·sides - were 8 feet thick. Within a few more years, this complex will be completely overgrown with radioactive vegetation."
    - 37. Platform (NLS125) (page 123), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This abandoned platform on Kidrenen Island, Enewetak Atoll, continues to rust away."
    - 38. Coconut Graveyard (NLS240) (page 125), 2011 (Box 1)
      "The residual levels of Cesium 137 (half-life of 30 years) absorbed into the coconuts on Eneu Island, Bikini Atoll, are still too high for human consumption to be safe."
    - 39. Burnt Palms (NLS184) (page 141), 2011 (Box 1)
      "Eneu Island, Bikini Atoll."
    - 40. Nuclear Dome (NLS111) (page 105), 2011 (Box 1)
      "The nuclear detonation 'Cactus' created a crater 30 feet deep and 350 feet wide at the northern tip of Runit Island, Enewetak Atoll. During the period of 'clean-up,' 111,000 cubic yards of radioactively contaminated soil and debris were entombed beneath an 18-inch-thick concrete dome. It took three years and cost $120 million to collect the debris. The crypt is constructed of 358 concrete panels that were built at the site. Later, male workers from the Department of Energy painted oil can red and placed it at the top of the dome. They then painted a large pink circle around the oil can. From the air, this nuclear dome looks like a huge breast."
    - 41. Cables Nest (NLS194) (page 135), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This bunker became a refuge for island creatures. As I was photographing, a large coconut crab, weighing about 30 pounds, moved deliberately through the darkened hallways. The sound of the crab's movements and the pools of standing, possibly contaminated water made me uneasy as I investigated the chambers. A noddy bird, a white-capped dark brown tem, has built its nest atop these abandoned electrical cables."
    - 42. Bunker Interior (NLS192) (page 133), 2011 (Box 1)
      "Although most of the bunkers were sealed during the 1970s, this bunker of Lele Island, Bikini Atoll, was left open."
    - 43. Bomb Assembly Building (NLS248) (page 127), 2011 (Box 1)
      "This building on Eneu Island, Bikini Atoll, was used by scientists and technicians of the University of California Radiation Laboratory to assemble nuclear devices used in the tests."
    - 44. Ruin (NLS227) (page 143), 2011 (Box 1)
      "Rusting ruin near the Bravo Crater, Bikini Atoll."
  - Panorama
    - 45. Trinity Site (NLS93) (page 29), 2011 (Box 2)
      "This is the site of the world's first nuclear explosion. It occurred on July 16, 1945, at 5:29:45 a.m. Mountain War Time on the Alamogordo Bombing and Gunnery Range of the White Sands Proving Ground in the Jornada del Muerto desert in New Mexico. The 20 kiloton 'Trinity' explosion was the birth of the Atomic Age."
      Only center of the image is used in the book.